欢迎回来, 在这个视频中我们将讨论有限自动机
Welcome back. In this video we're going to talk about finite automata
我们将在以后的视频中看到这是一个很好的实现模型
which we'll see in future videos are a good implementation model for regular
在前几个视频中, 我们一直在讨论正则表达式
expressions. So in the last few videos, we've been talking about regular
我们用作词汇的规范语言的表达式
expressions which we use as the specification language for lexical
分析, 在这个视频中, 我们要开始一些新的东西, 我们要讲的是
analysis. And, in this video we're gonna start something new. We're gonna talking
关于有限自动机它是作为一种实现机制的便利
about Finite Automata which are the For a convenience as an implementation mechanism
对于正则表达式, 所以正则表达式和有限自动机是非常重要的
for regular expressions. And so regular expressions and finite automaton are very
密切相关, 结果是它们可以指定完全相同的语言
close related. It turns out that they can specify exactly the same languages called
常规语言, 我们不会在这门课上证明但是我们一定会
the regular languages. We won't prove that in this course but we'll certainly make
利用这个事实, 那么, 沿着, 什么是有限自动机？好, 这是
use of that fact. So, moving right along, What is a finite automaton? Well, here is
一个典型的定义, 你们可能在自动机理论教科书中看到。
a typical definition as you might see in a automaton theory textbook. Finite
自动机由一个输入字母表组成, 因此, 它是一组字符
automaton consists of an input alphabet. So, it's a set of characters that it can
阅读, 它有有限的状态, 我们应该强调一下, 这是
read. It has this finite set of states. We should probably emphasize that. This is
使它成为有限自动机的原因是它有一些状态可以是
what makes it a finite automaton is that it has some set of states that it can be
其中一个状态是特殊的, 它被指定为起始状态。
in. One of those states is special and it's designated as the start state. Some
国家的子集是接受状态所以这些是状态, 但是, 嗯,
subset of the states are accepting states so these are the states that. But, well,
我们会在一分钟内发现更多, 但直觉上, 如果自动机终止,
we'll just find that more in a minute but intuitively, if the automaton terminates,
在读取了其中一个输入之后, 它接受输入。
after reading some input on one of these takes that it accepts the input.
否则, 它会拒绝输入最终自动机有一些
Otherwise, it rejects the input and finally the automaton has some set of
状态转换在一个状态, 它们可以读取一些输入然后切换到另一个状态
state transitions that is in one state, they can read some input and go to another
状态, 让我们看一下更详细的情况在有限的情况下
state. So let's look at that little more detail so a transition in a finite
自动机, 如果我在这里, 在这个例子中我写了一个特定的过渡
automaton. If I'm in, in this case I've written out one particular transition
这里, 我们在状态1, 我们读取输入A然后, 自动机可以移动到
here. We're in state one and we read the input A then, the automaton can move to
状态2, 好的, 对于自动机可能有很多不同的转换
state two, okay. And there could be lots of different transitions for the automaton
从不同的状态和不同的输入, 它的阅读方式如下, 如果我们
from different states and different inputs and its read the following way. If we're
在状态1的输入A中, 我们会进入状态2, 如果自动机结束
in state one on input A , we would go to state two. And, if the automaton ends in
一个接受状态当它到达输入端时它将会做什么
an accepting state when it gets to the end of the input that is going to do what's
叫做接受字符串意思是它会说yes, 那个字符串在
called accepting the string Meaning that it will say yes, That string was in the
这台机器的语言, 从直观上讲, 自动机从开始状态开始
language of this machine. So intuitively the automaton starts in the start state and
它不断地读取输入一个输入字符一次进行转换, 所以
it repeatedly reads inputs one input character at a time makes a transition. So
它会根据它的当前状态来判断它是怎样的
it'll see what kind of transition it can make out of its current state based on
这个输入到另一个状态如果它已经完成了输入它就在其中一个
that input to another state and if that's done ringing the input it's in one of the
最终的状态是它会接受的, 否则就会拒绝输入。
final states that it will accept. Otherwise is going to reject the input.
现在, 它拒绝的一种情况是, 如果它在一个状态中终止
Now, one of the situations in which it rejects, well, if it terminates In a state
S, 这不是最终的或接受的状态, 对吧？所以这就结束了
S, that's no one of the final or accepting states, okay? So that ends in any other
状态除了一个接受状态, 它会拒绝, 如果机器
state besides one of the accepting states and it's going to reject. If the machine
被卡住了, 这意味着它发现自己处于一种状态并且没有这种转变
gets stuck, Meaning it finds itself in a state and there's no transition of that
输入的状态, 特别地, 假设在某种状态下, 作为一个新闻
state on the input. So in particular, let's say that in some state as a news and
输入是A, 没有过渡, 每个状态没有指定的转换
the input is A, and there's no transition. There's no transition specified per state
作为输入A所以机器不能移动任何地方它会被卡住, 这也是
as an input A so the machine can't move anywhere and it get stuck and that's also
一个拒绝的状态, 所以在这两种情况下, 如果你能到达
a rejecting state. And so in these two situations, if, if you either get to the
输入的结束, 它不是在最终状态或者, 如果它永远不会到达
end of the input and it's not in a final state or. If it never reaches the end of
输入, 因为它可以卡住, 这两种情况都拒绝了字符串。
the input because it can stuck and both of those cases it rejects the string. That
字符串不是在有限自动机的语言中, 现在有一个
string is not in the language of the finite automaton. Now there's an
有限自动机的替代符号我认为更直观
alternative notation for Finite Automata that I think is more intuitive for
举个例子, 我们要强调的是写这个坐骑的方法
examples and so we're going to emphasize that way of writing the mount. In this
符号a状态被表示为一个已知的图形, 它画出一个大圆。
notation a state is represented as a known graph which just draws a big circle. The
起始状态被表示为一个节点, 它有一个边或一个箭头, 没有
start state is represented as a node that has an edge or an arrow into it with no
源, 这是向节点的过渡但没有源节点
source. So, this is a transition into the node but no source node that it comes from
这就表示了唯一的开始状态, 一个接受状态被绘制成一个节点的智慧
and that indicates the unique start state. An accepting state is drawn as a node wit
像这样的双圈, 最后一个过渡被画成一条边
h just double circles like this. And finally a transition is drawn as an edge
在图的两个节点之间, 这是这个状态下的时间
between two nodes of the graph. So with this as the time in this state that I'm
在蓝色圈中, 我读了输入a然后我就可以移动到这个状态了
circling in blue and I read the input a well then I can move to this state at, at
箭头的尾部, 现在, 我们来做一个简单的例子, 让我们试着把它写出来
the tail of the arrow. So now, let's do a simple example. Let's try to write up the
只接受单个数字1的自动机, 所以我们只需要启动状态。
automaton that accepts only the single digit one. So all we need is start state.
也可能想要一个接受的状态现在的问题是
And will probably want an accepting state as well and now the questions is what do
我们把两者放在两者之间？好吧, 这里会有某种过渡
we put in between the two? Well, there would be some kind of transition here and
这是一个很好的猜测, 如果机器读取了这个转换, 我们应该进行这个转换。
it's a good guess that we should take that transition if the machine reads the one.
现在让我花点时间来谈谈机器是如何执行的
Now let me take a moment here to talk about how the machine executes so let's
标记这些状态, 我们称这个状态为a我们称这个状态为b, 好的
label these states. Let's call this state a and let's call this state b, okay. So
机器会有一些输入, 好的, 我们可以把输入写出来
the machine will have some input. Okay, and we can write that input out will be
这里, 我们说, 我们有单个字符1, 它从一些开始
here. So let's just say, we have the single character one and it begins in some
状态即起始状态, 因此, 机器的一个配置是状态
state namely the start state. And so, one configuration of the machine is the state
它是in和输入, 通常我们会指出它在输入中的位置
that it is in And the input. And typically we would indicate where it is in the input
通过一个指针, 说明它在输入中是什么位置, 重要的是
by just a pointers saying what position it is in the input. And, the important thing
要知道输入, 听不清输入指针总是前进的, 所以, 当
to know about input in [inaudible] the input pointer always advances. So, when
我们, 或者它只是在我们读取字符输入时, 输入指针移动
we, or it only advances so when we read a character input, the input pointer moves
对右边, 它永远不会后退, 好的, 从a状态开始, 我们有一个规则。
to the right and it never moves back. Alright, So from state a, we have a rule.
我们可以看到, 我们在状态a, 下一个输入字符是1, 这允许
We can see that we're in state a. The next input character is a one and that allows
我们要过渡到状态b现在b在b状态下, 在哪里
us to take a transition to state b and so now where b in state b and where as our
输入点很好, 它超出了输入的末端表明我们已经结束了
input point well it's beyond the end of the input indicating we are at the end of
输入, 现在这是。我们处于一个接受状态, 我们通过了
the input. And so now this is. We are in an accepting state and we pass the end of
输入, 所以我们接受, 好吧, 我们再执行一次, 我们开始
the input and so we accept. Okay? So let's, do another execution. So we start
在状态a中, 让我们输入字符串0, 好的, 我想要画出来
in state a and let's take as our input the string zero. Okay. And I'd like to draw
这个指针, 实际上我应该在输入之前把它画出来所以我们会把它放在
the pointer. Actually I should have drawn it before the input so we'll al ways put
两个输入元素之间的指针。在本例中, 它仅仅是左边的
the pointer between two input elements. In this case it's a merely to the left of the
一个我们要读的, 在这个例子中我们是读零的所以在状态a中
one we're about to read. So in this case we're about read zero so in state a. Our
输入是零, 我们看一下我们的机器, 我们看到在零上没有过渡。
input is zero. We look at our machine. We see that there is no transition on zero.
好吧, 所以机器就卡住了, 它根本不动, 这个
All right? And so the machine stays stuck. It doesn't make any move at all and this
这是我们的最终配置, 我们可以看到, 我们并没有在输入的末尾
is our final configuration. And we could see that we're not at the end of the input
这是一个拒绝, 在这种情况下机器会拒绝这个字符串
and so this is a reject. Okay, so in this case the machine rejects that string as
不是在机器的语言中, 我们再举一个例子, 假设
not being in the language of the machine. Let's do one more example. Let's say that
我们处于状态, 我们总是从状态a和开始状态开始,
we're in state, well we're always beginning in state a and the start state,
假设我们输入的是字符串10, 好吗？我们的输入指针是
and let's say our input this time is the string ten, okay? And our input pointer is
好了, 我们在状态a, 输入是1, 所以我们要移动到
there. All right? So again we're in state a. The input is a one and so we'll move to
状态b, 现在输入没有改变, 只是输入点改变了, 但我还是
state b. And now the input doesn't change. Just the input point changes but I'll just
复制输入, 以显示差异, 现在输入指针有
copy the input over to show the difference. Now the input pointer has
因为我们已经读过了输入的一个字符现在我们在另一个状态。
advanced cuz we've read one character of input and now we're in another state. And
现在我们可以看到, 我们在状态b下, 我们的下一个输入是零, 没有
now we can see that we're in state b. Our next input is zero and there is no
从状态b过渡到0, 所以即使我们处于接受状态b
transition on zero from state b and so even though we're in an accepting state, b
作为最终的状态, 它是一个接受状态我们还没有完全消耗掉
as a final state, it's one of the accept state and we haven't consumed the entire
输入, 所以这台机器也会拒绝这个字符串所以这也是a
input. And so this, The machine also rejects this string so this is also a
拒绝, 一般来说, 我们可以讨论一种有限自动机的语言
reject. And in general we can talk about the language. Of a finite automata that is
等于一组被接受的字符串, 对吧？所以有限的语言
equal to the set of...accepted strings. Okay? So the language of a finite
自动机, 当我说到有限自动机的语言时, 我指的是
automaton, when I'm talking about the language of a finite automaton, I mean the
自动机接受的一组字符串, 现在我们来做一个更复杂的例子。
set of strings that the automaton accepts. So now let's do a more complex example.
让我们试着写出一个自动机来接受任意数量的一个
Let's try to write out an automaton that accepts any number of one followed by a
单零, 再一次需要一个启动状态我们还需要一个final
single zero. So once again well need a start state and we'll also need a final
状态, 现在我们先来考虑最短的字符串是什么
state and now let's start by thinking about what's the shortest string is that's
在这台机器的语言中, 在这种情况下, 我们知道它必须以a结尾
in the language of this machine. So in this case, we know it has to end in a
是零, 所以0肯定是, 零跃迁必须是最后一个
singl e zero. So a zero definitely has to be, a zero transition has to be the last
移动, 在这个0之前可以有任意数量的什么？在一个特定的地方
move and before that zero can come any number of what? In a particular there
可能不是1, 所以这台机器的一个转变是从开始状态输入到输入
could be no 1's. So one transition in this machine is that from start state on input
零, 我们可以进入最终状态因为单个字符串包含
zero we can definitely go to the final state because the single string consisting
在一个零的情况下不是这台机器的语言, 现在唯一的问题是
of a single zero isn't the language of this machine. And now the only question is
我们如何编码任意数量的1可以继续为0呢？好吧, 有
how do we encode the fact that any number of 1's can proceed to zero? Well, there is
这是一种简单的方法, 我们可以在开始状态下添加一个, 听不清
an easy way to do that. We can just add a [inaudible] by the start state. And take
这个转变, 如果我们读一下, 这意味着什么？这意味着我们将
that transition if we read at one. And what does this mean? This means that we'll
停留在状态, 状态越久我们读的是1, 当我们阅读的时候
stay in the state, state as longer are we're reading 1's and as soon as we read
0, 我们将移到最终状态因为这必须是最后的状态
zero, we'll move to the final state because that has to be the end of the
如果机器要接受它, 我们来做几个例子
string if the machine is going to accept it. So let's do a couple of examples to
让我们相信这是可行的, 我再标记一下这个状态, 这是状态
convince ourselves that this works. Let me label this state?s again. So this is state
a, 这是stat b, 我们写一下状态和输入, 我们从这里开始
a, and that's stat b. So Let's write out here states and input. So we'll begin in
状态a, 让我们输入110, 好的, 我们先来做一个接受的例子
state a and let's take as input 110, okay. So let's do an accepting case first. All
好的, 我们的输入指针从第一个字符的左边开始, 所以, 我们在
right, So our input pointer begins to the left of the first character. So, we're in
状态a在开始状态, 我们读了一个, 说我们应该选a
state a in start state. We're reading a one and that says we should take a
转换使我们回到状态a, 所以, 我们推进输入指针。
transition that puts us back in state a. And so, we advance the input pointer. And
现在我们使用第一个, 再一次, 我们在状态a和下一个输入
now we consume the first one and, and again we're in state a and the next input
是一个, 所以我们要对状态a进行另一个转换, 输入清洁器会
is a one so we'll make another transition to state a. And the input cleaner will
前进, 现在我们在状态a下一个输入是0, 所以我们要
advance. So now we're in state a and the next input is a zero and so we'll take the
转换到b现在在这个配置中, 所以输入指针有
transition to b and now in this configuration, so the input pointer has
到达输入的末端我们处于一个接受状态, 所以机器
reached the end of the input we're in an accepting state and so the machine
接受。110是在这台机器的语言中, 现在我们来举个例子
accepts. 110 is in the language of this machine. So now let's do an example where
我们会拒绝输入, 我们会从a和a开始
we will reject the input. And what configuration do we begin in and again a
一个有限自动机的构型也就是说, 你知道一个点
configuration for a finite automaton that just means you know a point in the
执行it alwa是由一个状态和一个输入指针的位置组成的。
execution it alwa ys consist of a state and a position of the, the input pointer.
所以我们的初始状态是a现在我们来选择弦, 我不知道,
So our initial state is a and now let's just choose the string. I don't know,
让我们取100, 让我们确认这不是在机器的语言中。
let's take 100 and let's confirm that this is not in the language of the machine. All
好的, 我们从状态a开始, 输入指针在这里, 现在我们读了一个
right, So we begin in state a and our input pointer is there. Now we read a one
这意味着, 你知道, 这是从状态转换为1的状态, 我们待在
and that means, well, you know. So it's from state a transition of one. We stay in
状态a和输入指针前进, 现在我们看到一个0, 从状态a和
state a and the input pointer advances. And now we see a zero. So from state a and
输入零, 我们向状态b过渡, 现在输入点在这里, 现在,
input zero, we make a transition to state b. And now the input point is here so now,
我们在状态b, 我们有一个0的输入但是没有转换b和
we're in state b and we have an input of zero but there is no transition the b and
0, b根本就没有转变所以机器就卡住了
zero, there are no transitions out of b at all and so the machine gets stuck, it
无法到达输入的en, 尽管我们在接受
can't get to the en of the input and again, even though we're in an accepting
状态, 我们还没有读取整个输入, 所以这意味着机器会拒绝。
state we haven't read the entire input yet and so that means the machine will reject.
所以, 100不是这台机器的语言。
And so, 100 is not in the language of this machine.